Eight years ago, I was haunted by an evil spirit.
قبل ثمان سنوات مسّتني روح شريرة.
I was 25 at the time,
كان عمري حينها 25 عاماً،
and I was living in a tiny house behind someone else's house
وكنت أعيش في منزل صغير خلف منزل أحد اخر
in Los Angeles.
في مدينة لوس أنجلوس.
It was this guest house, it had kind of been dilapidated,
كان بيت ضيافة وقد كان متداعياً نوعاً ما،
not taken care of for a long time.
لم يعتنى به لفترة طويلة.
And one night, I was sitting there
و في إحدى الليالي كنت جالسة هناك
and I got this really spooky feeling,
و شعرت بهذا الشعور المخيف حقاً،
kind of the feeling like you're being watched.
شعور كأنك مراقب.
But no one was there except my two dogs,
و لكن لم يكن هناك من أحد ما عدا كلبي الإثنين،
and they were just chewing their feet.
وكانا يمضغان أقدامهما فحسب.
And I looked around. No one was there.
فنظرت حولي. لا يوجد أحد هناك.
And I thought, OK, it's just my imagination.
وفكرت، حسناً، إنها مخيلتي فحسب.
But the feeling just kept getting worse,
ولكن الشعور ازداد سوءاً،
and I started to feel this pressure in my chest,
وبدأت أشعر بهذا الثقل على صدري،
sort of like the feeling when you get bad news.
مثل الشعور عندما تتلقى أخبارً سيئة.
But it started to sink lower and lower
ولكنه بدأ يغوص أعمق وأعمق بداخلي
and almost hurt.
بل يأذيني حتى.
And over the course of that week, this feeling got worse and worse,
وخلال ذلك الأسبوع أصبح هذا الشعور أسوء وأسوء،
and I started to become convinced that something was there
وبدأت أقتنع أن شيئاً ما هناك
in my little guest house, haunting me.
في بيت صيافتي الصغير يطاردني.
And I started to hear these sounds,
وبدأت أسمع تلك الأصوات،
this "whoosh," kind of whisper, like something passing through me.
ذلك الصوت مثل "هوووش،" وكأن شيئاً ما يعبر بجانبي.
I called my best friend, Claire, and said,
اتصلت بصديقتي المقربة كلير وقلت لها:
"I know this is going to sound crazy,
"أعلم أن هذا سيبدو جنونياً،
but, um ...
و لكن، امممم
I think there's a ghost in my house, and I need to get rid of it."
أعتقد أنه يوجد شبح في منزلي، وأحتاج أن أتخلص منه."
And she said -- she's very open-minded -- and she said,
فقالت -- هي صاحبة عقل منفتح جداً -- فقالت:
"I don't think you're crazy.
"لا أعتقد أنك مجنونة.
I think you just need to do a cleansing ritual."
أعتقد أنك فقط بحاجة إلى طقس تطهيري"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"So get some sage and burn it,
"لذلك احصلي على بعض المريمية وأحرقيها،
and tell it to go away."
وأخبريه أن يغادر."
So I said, "OK," and I went and I bought sage.
لذلك قلت "حسنا" وذهبت واشتريت مريمية.
I had never done this before, so I set the sage on fire,
لم أفعل هذا مطلقاً من قبل، لذلك أحرقت المريمية،
waved it about, and said, "Go away! This is my house! I live here.
لوّحت بها ثم قلت: "ارحل! هذا بيتي أنا! أنا أعيش هنا.
You don't live here!"
أما أنت فلا تعيش هنا!"
But the feeling stayed. Nothing got better.
و لكن الشعور استمر ولم يتحسّن شيئ.
And then I started to think,
وبعد ذلك بدات أفكر،
OK, well now this thing is probably just laughing at me,
حسناً من المحتمل أن هذا الشيئ يضحك علي الآن،
because it hasn't left,
لانه لم يرحل،
and I probably just look like this impotent, powerless thing
ولربما أبدو كشيئ واهن عديم القوة فحسب
that couldn't get it to go away.
غير قادر على جعله يرحل.
So every day I'd come home
لذلك كل يوم أرجع للمنزل
and you guys, this feeling got so bad that -- I mean, I'm laughing at it now --
ويا رفاق هذا الشعور أصبح سيئاً لدرجة -- أنا أضحك عليه الآن --
but I would sit there in bed and cry every night.
و لكنني كنت أجلس هناك على سريري و أبكي كل ليلة.
And the feeling on my chest got worse and worse.
ثم أصبح الشعور على صدري أسوء وأسوء.
It was physically painful.
كان مؤلماً جسدياً.
And I even went to a psychiatrist
وذهبت حتى لطبيبة نفسية
and tried to get her to prescribe me medicine,
وحاولت أن أجعلها تصف لي أدوية،
and she wouldn't just because I don't have schizophrenia, OK.
ولكنها رفضت لأني لا أعاني من انفصام الشخصية، حسناً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So finally I got on the internet, and I Googled "hauntings."
لذلك أخيراً اتجهت للإنترنت وبحثت على غوغل "مسكون بالأرواح."
And I came upon this forum of ghost hunters.
ووجدت هذا المنتدى عن صائدي الأشباح.
But these were a special kind of ghost hunters --
ولكنهم نوع خاص من صائدي الأشباح --
they were skeptics.
كانوا متشككين.
They believed that every case of ghosts that they had investigated so far
كانوا يؤمنون بأن كل حالات الأشباح التي تحرّوا عنها حتى الآن
had been explained away by science.
فسّرها العلم.
And I was like, "OK, smart guys, this is what's happening to me,
فقلت: "حسناً، أيها الأذكياء، هذا هو ما يحدث معي،
and if you have an explanation for me, I would love to hear it."
وإن كان لديكم تفسير لي أود سماعه."
And one of them said, "OK.
وقال أحدهم: "حسناً.
Um, have you heard of carbon monoxide poisoning?"
هل سمعتي من قبل عن تسمّم أول أكسيد الكربون؟"
And I said, "Yeah.
فقلت: "نعم.
Like, gas poisoning?"
مثل تسمّم الغاز؟"
Carbon monoxide poisoning is when you have a gas leak
يحدث تسمم أول أكسيد الكربون عندما يحدث تسرب غاز
leaking into your home.
في منزلك.
I looked it up, and the symptoms of carbon monoxide poisoning
بحثت عنه، و عن أعراض تسمّم أول أكسيد الكربون
include a pressure on your chest,
المتضمنة لثقل على الصدر
auditory hallucinations -- whoosh --
وهلاوس سمعية -- هوووش --
and an unexplained feeling of dread.
وشعور بالفزع ليس له تفسير.
So that night, I called the gas company.
لذلك اتصلت بشركة الغاز في تلك الليلة.
I said, "I have an emergency. I need you to come out.
وقلت: "عندي حالة طارئة تستلزم وجودكم
I don't want to get into the story now, but I need you to come out."
لا أريد أن أخوض في القصة الآن ولكنني بحاجة إلى حضوركم."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
They came out. I said, "I suspect a gas leak."
عندما أتوا قلت لهم: "أشك في تسرب غاز."
They brought their carbon monoxide detector,
أحضروا الجهاز الكاشف عن أول أكسيد الكربون
and the man said,
و قال الرجل:
"It's a really good thing that you called us tonight,
"اتصالك بنا الليلة أمر جيّد حقاً،
because you could have been dead very soon."
لأنك كنت من الممكن أن تموتي قريباً جداً."
Thirty-seven percent of Americans believe in haunted houses,
يؤمن 37% من الأمريكيين بالمنازل المسكونة،
and I wonder how many of them have been in one
وأتسائل كم منهم تواجد في أحدها
and how many of them have been in danger.
وكم منهم تعرض للخطر.
So that haunting story has led me to my job.
ولذلك قادتني قصة مطاردة الأرواح تلك إلي وظيفتي.
I'm an investigator, and I'm an investigator in two senses:
أنا محققة، وأعني بذلك شيئين اثنين:
I'm an investigative journalist,
أنا صحفية استقصائية،
and I'm also an investigator of the claims of the paranormal
ومحققة أيضاً في ادعاءات الأشياء الخارقة للعادة
and claims of the spiritual.
وادعاءات الأرواح.
And that means a few things.
ويعني هذا بضعة أشياء.
Sometimes that means that I'm pretending to need an exorcism
أحياناً يعني هذا أن أدّعي أنني أحتاج إلى تعويذة لطرد الروح الشريرة
so I can get -- yes, that's right! -- so I can go to an exorcist
لكي أستطيع أن -- نعم هذا صحيح! -- لذلك أذهب لطارد الأرواح
and see if he's using gimmicks or psychological tricks
وأرى إن كان يستخدم حيل أو خدع نفسية
to try to convince someone that they're possessed.
لكي يقنع أحدهم أنه مستحوذ عليه.
Sometimes that means I'm going undercover in a fringe group
وأحياناً يعني ذلك أن أذهب متخفية في مجموعة ذات أراء متطرفة
which I report on for a podcast that I co-host.
والتي أبلغ عنها على مدونة صوتية اشترك في استضافتها.
And I've done over 70 investigations like this with my co-host, Ross.
وقد قمت بأكثر من 70 تحقيق مثل هذا مع شريكي روس.
I would love to tell you that nine times out of 10, science wins,
وأود أن أقول لكم أنه في 9 مرات من أصل 10 يفوز العلم،
saves the day, it's all explained.
وينقذ اليوم، ويفسر كل شيئ.
That's not true.
و هذا ليس صحيحاً.
The truth is, 10 times out of 10, science wins, it saves the day.
الحقيقة أنه في 10 مرات من أصل 10 يفوز العلم وينقذ اليوم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And that doesn't mean there's no such thing as a mystery.
وهذا لا يعني أنه لا وجود لشيئ يدعى الغموض.
Of course there are mysteries, but a mystery is a mystery.
بالطبع توجد أشياء غامضة ولكن الأشياء الغامضة تكون غامضة.
It is not a ghost.
وهي ليست خيالاً.
Now, I believe there are two kinds of truth,
الآن أنا أؤمن بوجود نوعين من الحقيقة،
and it's taken me a while to get to this place, but I think this is right,
وقد أخذ مني الأمر فترة لأصل لهذا الرأي،
so hear me out.
لذلك استمعوا.
I think there is outer truth and there's inner truth.
أعتقد أنه يوجد حقيقة خارجية وأخرى داخلية.
So if you say to me,
لذلك لو قلت لي:
"There was a man named Jesus and he once existed,"
"كان يوجد رجل يسمى المسيح يوماً ما،"
that's outer truth, right?
هذه حقيقة خارجية، صحيح؟
And we can go and look at the historical record.
ويمكننا أن نذهب وننظر للسجلات التاريخية.
We can determine whether that seems to be true.
ويمكننا أن نحدّد ما إذا كانت هذه تبدو حقيقية.
And I would argue, it does seem to be true.
وكنت سأجادل أن هذه تبدو حقيقة.
If you say, "Jesus rose from the dead," -- ooh, trickier.
إذا ما قلت "بعث المسيح بعد الموت" أوه أصعب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I would say that's an outer-truth claim,
كنت سأقول أن هذا ادعاء للحقيقة الخارجية،
because he physically rose or he didn't.
لأنه بعث فعلاً أو لم يبعث.
I'm not going to get into whether he rose or he didn't,
سوف لن أدخل في تفاصيل ما إذا كان بعث فعلاً أو لا،
but I would say that's an outer-truth claim.
ولكن سأقول أن هذا ادعاء للحقيقة الخارجية.
It happened or it didn't happen.
سواء حدثت أو لم تحدث.
But if you say, "I don't care whether he rose from the dead.
لكن إذا قلت: "أنا لا أهتم إذا ما كان بعث بعد الموت.
It's symbolically important to me,
فهو شيئ هام رمزياً بالنسبة لي،
and that metaphor is so meaningful, so purposeful to me,
وهذه الإستعاره تعني لي الكثير وهي هادفة جداً،
and I'm not going to try to persuade you of it,"
ولن أحاول أن أقنعك بها،"
now you've moved it from outer truth to inner truth,
الآن أنت نقلتها من الحقيقة الخارجية للحقيقة الداخلية،
from science to art.
من العلم للفن.
And I think we have a tendency to not be clear about this,
وأعتقد أننا نميل أن لا نكون واضحين بخصوصها،
to try to move our inner truths to outer truths,
وأن نحاول نقل حقائقنا الداخلية لأخرى خارجية،
or to not be fair about it to each other,
وأن لا نكون عادلين بخصوصها مع بعضنا البعض،
and when people are telling us their inner truths,
وعندما يخبرنا الناس عن حقائقهم الداخلية،
to try to make them defend them by outer-truth standards.
وأن نحاول جعلهم يدافعون عنها بمعايير الحقيقة الخارجية.
So I'm talking here about outer truth, about objective things.
لذلك أنا أتحدث هنا عن الحقيقة الخارجية، عن الأشياء الموضوعية.
And there was an objective reality in my haunted house, right?
وكانت توجد حقيقة موضوعية في بيتي المسكون، صحيح؟
Now that I've told you about the gas leak,
والآن بعد أن أخبرتكم عن تسرّب الغاز،
I doubt a single person here would be like,
أشك أن شخصاً واحداً هنا سيقول:
"I still think there was a ghost, too" --
"مازلت أعتقد انه كان يوجد شبح أيضاً" --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
because as soon as we have these scientific explanations,
لأنه بمجرد حصولنا على هذه التفسيرات العلمية،
we know to give up the ghost.
حينها نتعلم أن نتخلى عن فكرة الشبح.
We use these things as stopgaps for things that we can't explain.
نحن نستخدم هذه الأشياء كبديل للأشياء التي لا يمكننا تفسيرها.
We don't believe them because of evidence;
نحن لا نصدقهم لوجود دليل؛
we believe them because of a lack of evidence.
بل نصدقهم لعدم وجود دليل.
So there is a group in Los Angeles
ولذلك توجد مجموعة في لوس انجلوس
called the Independent Investigations Group, or the IIG,
تسمى مجموعة التحقيقات المستقلة أو (م ت م)،
and they do great work.
وهم يقومون بعمل رائع.
They'll give a $10,000 prize
هم سيعطون جائزة 10،000 دولار
to anyone who can show, under scientific conditions,
لأي أحد يظهر تحت ظروف علمية،
that they have a paranormal ability.
أن لديه قدرات خارقة للعادة.
No one's done it yet,
ولا يوجد أحد قام بذلك حتى الآن،
but they've had a couple people who claim that they were clairaudients,
ولكن بعض الناس إدعو قدرات سمعية خارقة،
which means that they can hear voices either from the great beyond
الشيئ الذي يعني أنهم يقدرون على سماع أصوات إما من الجانب الآخر العظيم
or they can read minds.
أو بإمكانهم قراءة الأفكار.
And they had one person who was very sincere,
و قد كان لديهم شخص صادق جداً،
who believed that he could read minds.
والذي كان يؤمن أنه يمكنه أن يعرف ما يفكر به الآخرون.
So they set up a test with him, and this is the way it always works.
فقاموا بإجراء اختبار له وكانت هذه الطريقة التي كانوا يتبعونها.
The group says, "OK, we have a protocol,
قالت المجموعة: "حسناً، لدينا نظام،
we have a way to scientifically test this.
لدينا طريقة علمية لاختبار ذلك.
Do you agree with it?"
هل تتفق معها؟"
The person says yes. Then they test it.
وافق الشخص. وقاموا بإجراء الاختبار.
It's very important that both sides agree.
ومن المهم جداً أن يوافق الطرفان.
They did that, they tested him.
وقاموا بهذا واختبروه.
They said, "OK, you know what?
وقالوا حسناً، أتعلم ماذا؟
You weren't able to predict what Lisa was thinking.
أنت لم تكن قادراً على التنبئ بما تفكر به ليزا.
It matched up about the same as chance.
وكانت مطابقة تقريباً للصدفة.
Looks like you don't have the power."
يبدو أنك لا تملك هذه القوة الخارقة."
And that gave them the opportunity
وأعطاهم هذا الفرصة
to compassionately sit down with him and have a very difficult discussion,
أن يجلسوا معه برحمه وأن يخوضوا حوارً صعباً جداً،
which basically amounted to,
الذي كان ملخصه،
"Hey, we know you're sincere, and what that means is,
"نحن نعلم أنك صادق وهذا يعني
you do hear something in your head."
أنك بالفعل تسمع شيئاً في راسك."
And that guy got to make the very difficult decision,
وتوجب على ذلك الشخص أن يتخذ القرار الصعب جداً،
but really the life-changing decision about whether to go get help.
ولكنه حقاً قرار سيغير حياته إذا ما كان سيذهب لطلب المساعده أم لا.
We're actually helping people to make these connections
ونحن في الواقع نساعد الناس على عمل مثل هذه الاتصالات
that maybe before seemed like otherworldly explanations,
والتي من الممكن أن تبدو من قبل تفسيرات من عالم آخر،
help draw us into reality and maybe change our lives for the better.
فهي تساعدنا على الرجوع للواقع وتغيير حياتنا للأفضل.
Now, on the other hand, maybe one time it'll turn out to be true.
الآن من ناحية أخرى من الممكن في إحدى المرات أن تتحول لتصبح حقيقة.
Maybe we'll find out there are ghosts,
ربما نكتشف وجود أشباح،
and holy shit, it will be the best thing!
اللعنة! ستكون أفضل شيئ.
And every time I do one of these investigations,
وفي كل مرة أقوم فيها بإحدى هذه التحقيقات،
I still get so excited,
أصبح متحمسة جداً،
and I'm like 75 into them,
وأكون 75 % متفائلة بهم،
and still I swear on number 76, I'm going to be like, "This is the one!"
وما أزال أقسم بالرقم 76 وسأقول "هذه هي!"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Maybe I'm just eternally optimistic, but I hope I never lose this hope,
ربما أنا متفائلة ولكني آمل أن لا أفقد الأمل أبداً،
and I invite you to take this same attitude
وأدعوكم أن تتبعوا نفس النهج
when people share their outer beliefs with you.
عندما يشارككم الناس معتقداتهم الخارجية.
When talking about testable claims,
وعندما يدور الحديث عن ادعاءات قابلة للاختبار،
respect them enough to ask these good questions.
احترموهم بالقدر الكافي لتسألوهم أسئلة جيدة.
Challenge and see how you can examine them together,
تحدوا وانظروا كيف يمكنكم اختبار هذه الادعاءات معاً،
because there's this idea that you can't respect a belief
لأن هناك فكرة انه لايمكنك أن تحترم معتقداً
and still challenge it, but that's not true.
وتختبره في نفس الوقت ولكن هذا ليس صحيح.
When we jiggle the lock, when we test the claim,
عندما نختبر الادعاء،
we're saying, OK, I respect you, I'm listening to what you're saying,
نقول، حسناً، أنا أحترمك وأستمع لما تقول،
I'm going to test it out with you.
وسأقوم باختباره معك.
We've all had that experience where you're telling someone something,
مررنا جميعنا بتلك التجربة عندما تخبر شخصاً ما شيئاً ما،
and they're like, "Oh, that's really interesting, yeah,"
فيكون رد فعله، "حسناً، إنه شيئ مثير حقاً،"
you know you're being had.
تعلم أنهم يسمعونك.
But when someone says, "Really? Huh.
و لكن حينما يقول شخص ما: "حقاً؟ هاه.
Sounds a little sketchy to me, but I'm listening,"
يبدو لي خيالياً نوعا ما ولكني أستمع."
you at least know you're being engaged and respected.
على الأقل تعلم أنهم ينصتون إليك ويحترمونك.
And that's the kind of attitude we should have with these claims.
وينبغي علينا اتباع مثل هذا السلوك مع هكذا ادعاءات.
That's showing someone that you care what they're saying.
أن تبيّن للشخص أنك مهتم بما يقوله.
That's respect.
ذلك هو الاحترام.
Now, yes, most of these searches will come up empty,
الآن، نعم، معظم هذه الأبحاث ستكون فارغة،
but that's how all of science works.
ولكن هذه هي طريقة عمل كل العلوم.
Every cure for cancer so far has not panned out,
جميع علاجات السرطان حتى الآن لم تنجح تماماً،
but we don't stop looking,
لكننا لا نتوقف عن البحث،
for two reasons.
لسببين اثنين:
Because number one, the answer matters.
لأنه أولاً الإجابة تهم.
Whether it's looking at the afterlife or the paranormal or the cure for cancer,
سواء كنا نبحث في البعث أو الظواهر الخارقة للطبيعة أو علاج السرطان،
it all amounts to the same question:
جميعها تؤدي لنفس السؤال:
How long will we be here?
إلى متى سنبقى هنا؟
And two, because looking for the truth,
وثانياً لأن البحث عن الحقيقة،
being open-minded,
كونك متفتح العقل،
and being willing to be wrong and to change your whole worldview
كونك مستعد لتقبل خطئك وتغيير نظرتك للعالم كلياً
is awe-inspiring.
هو شيئ مذهل.
I still get excited at ghost stories every single time.
ما أزال أتحمس لقصص الأشباح في كل مرة.
I still consider that every group I join might be right,
وما أزال أعتبر أن كل مجموعة انضم لها قد تكون على حق،
and I hope I never lose that hope.
وآمل ألا أفقد ذلك الأمل أبداً.
Let's all never lose that hope,
دعونا جميعاً ألا نفقد ذلك الأمل أبداً
because searching for what's out there
لأن البحث عن ما هو هناك بالخارج
helps us understand what's in here.
يساعدنا على أن نفهم ما يوجد هنا بالداخل.
And also, please have a carbon monoxide detector in your home.
ومن فضلكم احتفظوا بجهاز قياس أول أكسيد الكربون في بيوتكم.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)